-==www.RagBear.com==- 福尔摩斯探案集  第1季第6集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=- 校对: ptrpan
过来 小子
Come here, lad.
你在我领地里干什么?
What are you doing on my property?
我是来讨回
I've come to claim back
属于我的东西 先生
what's rightfully mine, sir.
那个小流氓
That thieving young rascal
偷了我一些马蹄铁
made off with some horseshoes
还有包钉子 从我铁匠铺里
and a bag of nails from my smithy.
你有什么证据?
Where is your proof?
证据就是 赃物就在那里
The proof is, I'll find them there.
你可不要逼我
Now, I don't want to be forced
去叫警察
to call the police.
这些人是我的客人
These people are guests of mine,
你却是私闯民宅 肖恩先生
but you are trespassing, Mr. Thorn.
我可不怕你 医生
I'm not afraid of you, Doctor.
从我的地盘滚出去
Get off my land!
斑点带子案
请尽快回来
Please, come back soon.
亲爱的 根本没什么
My dear, there is nothing
好担心的
whatever to worry about.
过不了几周我们就结婚了
We should be married in a few weeks.
我要启程回伦敦了
I'm just on my way back to London.
再见 先生 感谢您
Goodbye, sir, and thank you
这个周末我非常愉快
for a most pleasant weekend.
我一定会在提升我的棋艺
I mean to improve my game of chess
下次造访咱们再看
before my next visit.
对 我知道
Oh, yes, I see.
你是个不容小看的对手
You weren't an unworthy opponent.
谢谢 先生
Thank you, sir.
我去把珀西送到门口 父亲
I'm just seeing Percy down to the gates, Father.
驶到大门口等我 好吗
Drive on and wait for me by the gate, will you.
那家伙私闯民宅
The fellow was trespassing,
给他浸浸水 就是这样
he had a dunking, and that is all.
父亲 我不信肖恩会故意...
Father, I cannot believe that Thorn would deliberate -
该死 女人
Dammit, woman,
你也跟他们合谋反对我吗?
are you part of the conspiracy against me, too?
不 父亲 我住这儿
No, Father, I live here.
不会太久了
Not for much longer, eh,
你就要和那个阿米蒂其结婚了
once you marry that fellow Armitage.
嗯 怎么啦
Yes, what is it?
父亲 我的房间怎么回事?
Father, what has happened to my room?
工人们发现一处结构失调
The builders found a fault in the structure,
最好睡在你姐姐的房间里
better sleep in your sister's room
等他们修缮完毕
till they've finished working on it.
朱丽亚的房间 我不能睡那儿
Julia's room, I can't sleep in there.
怎么不能?
Why not, Pray?
我不能
I can't.
怎么了
What is the matter,
那屋子好得很
it's a perfectly good room.
我已经叫管家收拾了
I've instructed the housekeeper to prepare it for you.
去拿行李 搬过去 晚安
Now run along, your baggage, and goodnight.
你好啊 小美人 晚安
Hello there young beauty, good night, good night.
很抱歉 华生
I'm very sorry, Watson,
但今早人人都不走运
but it seems to be the common lot this morning.
什么?
What?
哈德森夫人被吵醒了
Mrs. Hudson has been roused,
她来叫我 我来叫你
she retorted on me, and I on you.
但现在才七点一刻
But it's only a quarter past seven,
房子着火了吗?
what is it, a fire?
不 不 是一位客户
No, No, a client.
一会才能烧起来 先生
This will take a moment to draw, sir.
但就一会儿 哈德森太太
But only a moment, Mrs. Hudson is a mistress
可是升火的行家
of the art of fire lighting.
啊 这是我最好的伙伴
Ah, this is my intimate friend
也是助手 华生医生
and associate, Dr. Watson,
你可以在他面前畅谈 就像在我面前一样
before whom you may speak as freely as before myself.
你好吗?
How do you do?
哈德森太太 你能不能
Mrs. Hudson, do you think you could
给这位女士来杯热咖啡
bring this young lady a hot cup of coffee,
我发现在你在颤抖
for I observed you are shivering.
我并不是冻得发抖
It is not cold which makes me shiver.
那是为什么?
What, then?
是害怕 福尔摩斯先生
It is fear, Mr. Holmes.
是恐惧
It is terror.
你无须害怕
You must not fear,
我们会把事情处理好
we shall set matters right,
不必疑虑
have no doubt.
今早你是乘火车来的
You have come by train, I see, this morning.
这么说你认识我?
You know me, then?
不 我只是看到了半截回程票
No, but I observed the second half of a return ticket
在你左手手套里
in the palm of your left glove.
你很早就动身了 先乘马车
You started early, but you had a drive
两轮马车 经过一段泥路
in a dog-cart, along heavy roads,
才到达火车站
before you reached the station.
这没什么神秘的 年轻的女士
There is no mystery, my dear lady,
您上衣的左边袖子
the left arm of your jacket
溅上了泥点
is spattered with mud
不少于七处
in no less than seven places,
泥迹还未干
the marks are fresh.
唯有一种交通工具
There is no vehicle
就是两轮马车 会溅起
save a dog-cart which throws up mud
这么特别的泥点
in that particular way,
而且只有当你坐在
and then only when you sit on
车夫左手边时才可能
the left-hand side of the driver.
你说的太对了
You are perfectly correct.
先生 我再也不能承受这种紧张了
Sir, I can stand the strain no longer;
再这样下去我要疯了
I shall go mad if it continues.
我从费林托夫人那里听说了你
I have heard of you from Mrs. Farintosh,
你曾帮助她度过了困境
whom you helped in the hour of her sore need.
费林托
Farintosh.
我亲爱的海伦
My dear Helen,
我很难给你什么建议
it is difficult for me to advise you
你给我的情况太少
since you present so few facts,
但我知道你是个聪明的姑娘
but I know you to be a sensible girl,
不会随便猜疑
not prone to hysterics.
我是你可怜的母亲的最老的朋友
I was one of your poor, dear mother's oldest friends.
我只能建议你 如果一直恐惧
I can only suggest that if your fears persist,
去找夏洛克・福尔摩斯先生
you should contact Mr. Sherlock Holmes,
贝克街221B
221B Baker Street.
费林托 对了 我记得那个案子
Farintosh, oh, yes, I do remember the case.
是关于头冠上的猫眼石
It concerned an opal tiara.
应该发生在你来之前 华生
I think it was before your time, Watson.
谢谢 哈德森太太
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
先生 你是否也可以帮助我呢?
Sir, do you not think you could help me, too?
目前 我还没办法酬谢你
At present it is out of my power to reward you,
但几周后我就要结婚了
but in a few weeks I should be married
到时就可以支配我的收入
with control of my own income.
我很乐意帮助你
I shall be happy to devote the same care
就像帮助你的朋友一样
to your case as to that of your friend.
至于酬谢 我的工作
As to reward my profession
本身就是酬劳
is its own reward;
但是你也可以
but you are at liberty to defray
随意付给我些酬劳 在你认为
whatever expenses I may be put to at the time
合适的时候
which suits you best.
现在请告诉我们事情的全部经过
And now I beg you, lay everything before us
以便于我们作出初步判断
which may help us form an opinion upon this matter.
我叫海伦・斯通
My name is Helen Stoner.
和我继父住在一起
I live with my stepfather,
格林斯比・罗依罗德医生
Dr. Grimesby Roylott,
他是英国最老的撒克逊家族
who is the last survivor of one of the oldest
唯一的后裔
Saxon families in England.
斯托克摩兰的罗依罗德
The Roylotts of Stoke Moran,
这个名字似曾相识
the name is familiar to me.
他的职业是医生
He is a doctor by profession,
经验丰富
a skilled one.
他曾经行医多年 名誉卓著
For some years he had a large and flourishing practice
在印度 加尔各答
in India, in Calcutta.
华生医生也曾在印度行医
Dr. Watson has also practiced medicine in India.
对 跟随诺森伯兰第五火枪团
Yes, attached to the Fifth Northumberland Fusiliers.
请继续 斯通小姐
Pray continue, Miss Stoner.
在加尔各答 他娶了我母亲
In Calcutta, he married my mother.
她是一名少校留下的年轻寡妇
She was the young widow of Major mother's remarriage,
当时我只有两岁 我姐姐朱丽亚五岁
and my sister, Julia, was five years older.
我母亲有一大笔钱
Our mother had a considerable sum of money -
一年进项不少于一千磅
not less than a thousand a year -
这些她全留给了罗依罗德医生
and this she bequeathed to Dr. Roylott entirely
让我们和他住
while we resided with him.
抱歉 你母亲过世了吗?
Forgive me, your mother has passed on?
我们回英国后不久
Shortly after our return to England,
她出了事
she was killed
一次铁路交通意外 靠近科尔的地方
in a railway accident near Crewe.
然后我的继父便放弃了
My stepfather then abandoned his attempts
在伦敦开始他事业的初衷
to establish himself in practice in London
带着我们搬回了他的祖屋
and took us to live in his ancestral house
就在斯托克摩兰
at Stoke Moran.
但你母亲留给你们的钱
But the money your mother left you
足以满足你们的需要
was enough for all your wants,
所以你们仍可以过富足的生活?
so that was no obstacle to your happiness?
我继父发生了可怕的转变
A terrible change came over my stepfather,
他不和人交朋友 也不去
instead of making friends and exchanging visits
拜访邻居
with our neighbors,
他们一开始十分高兴
who at first were overjoyed
看到罗依罗德家人回到故乡
to see a Roylott back in the family seat,
但他把自己关在房子里
he shut himself up in the house
沉湎于和人疯狂争斗
and indulged in ferocious quarrels.
从那时到现在 我们很难避免
At times it was and still is hard to keep him out
他进警察局
of the police courts.
他成了村中一霸
He's become the terror of the village.
他允许别人拜访吗
Does he permit any visitors?
不 除了我的未婚夫和一些流浪的吉普赛人
No, except my fianc?and some wandering gypsies.
吉普赛人?
Gypsies?
流浪者 他允许他们
Vagabonds, whom he has given leave
在他的土地上扎营
to encamp on his land.
有时 他和他们一出去就是好几天
Sometimes he goes away with them for days at a time.
你可以从我的描述中看出来
You can imagine from what I'm saying
我可怜的姐姐朱莉亚和我
that my poor sister Julia and I
生活中几乎没什么乐趣
had no great pleasure in our lives.
仆人都待不了多久
No servant would stay long
所有的家务都是我们俩做
so we did all the work of the house.
她年仅三十岁就去世了
She was but 30 when I lost her,
那时她的头发已经花白了
but already her hair had begun to whiten,
和我的一样
even as mine has.
你姐姐死了?
Your sister is dead?
就在两年前
Just two years ago.
这正是我想要和您讲的
It is of that I wish to talk to you.
在我们这样的生活中
Living the life we did,
几乎不可能见到
we were little likely to see anyone
跟我们地位年龄相仿的人
of our own age and position,
但偶尔我们也会允许有些拜访
but we were occasionally allowed short visits.
两年前
Two years ago,
朱丽亚遇到了一个半薪海军少校
Julia met a half-pay major of marines,
之后他们订婚了
to whom she became engaged.
征得你继父的同意了?
Your stepfather approved of the match?
他根本就没有一点反对
He raised no objection at all.
婚前两星期
A fortnight before the wedding,
发生了一件可怕的事
a terrible event occurred
夺走了我唯一的伙伴
which deprived me of my only companion.
请说的详细些
Praybe precise as to details.
这容易
It is easy,
那晚每一幕都烙在我脑海中
every event of that night is seared into my memory.
那天深夜 大约十一点
It was late, about 11:00,
朱丽亚跑到了我的屋里
Julia had come into my room.
他又在抽那些难闻的雪茄了
He's smoking those awful cigars again.
也许你婚礼前应该住这个房间里
Perhaps you should have this room until the wedding.
哦 海伦 我真幸福
Oh, Helen, oh, I feel so happy.
可我也担心把你一个人留在这里
And yet wretched that I'm leaving you here alone.
我迟早也会离开的
My turn will come.
我会想你的
I shall miss you.
不用 我会去看你
No, you won't, I'll come and stay.
另外 你的少校也答应给我
Besides, your major has promised to find me
介绍一个相同级别的军官
a brother officer of equal rank,
绝对比他英俊
and infinitely better looking.
亲爱的 怎么了?
My darling, what is the matter?
海伦 你听到过有人吹口哨吗
Helen, have you ever heard anyone whistle
在深夜里?
in the dead of night?
你睡觉时该不会吹口哨吧
I suppose you couldn't possibly whistle yourself, in your sleep?
当然不能 怎么了?
Certainly not, why?
这几天夜里
The last few nights,
大约凌晨三点
always about 3:00 in the morning,
我总会被微弱而清晰的口哨吵醒
I've been woken by a low, clear whistle.
我也说不出是哪儿传来的
I can't tell where it's coming from.
还以为你也听到了呢
I thought you might have heard it.
我睡得比你沉
I sleep more heavily than you.
可能是那些吉普赛人
It was probably those wretched gypsies.
算了 不管了
Well, never mind.
你们在晚上
Was it your custom always
总会锁好门窗吗?
to lock yourself in at night?
会的 我继父热爱
Always, my stepfather has a passion
饲养印度动物
for Indian animals.
有一只豹子 一只狒狒
A leopard and baboon
在我们庄园里活动
wander freely over the grounds.
朱莉亚和我总觉得不安全
Julia and I had no feelings of security
除非把门窗锁上
unless our doors and windows were locked.
我睡不着
I couldn't sleep,
有种很不好的预感
I had a vague feeling of misfortune.
朱丽亚
Julia!
救救我
Please help me.
哦 天哪 海伦 是带子
Oh, my God, Helen, It was the band...
一条斑点带子
the speckled band.
我去叫父亲
I'll get father.
不
No!
回房间去 孩子
Go into your room child,
这里我来处理
I'll deal with this.
很抱歉 先生们
I am sorry, gentlemen.
我姐姐和我很亲密
My sister and I were very close.
那是当然
Yes indeed.
多么悲伤的经历
What a mournful experience.
而你完全不知道是什么引起了
And you've no idea what might have caused -
这阵口哨和金属声
This whistle and metallic sound,
你肯定听到了?
you can swear to it?
我印象很深
It is my strong impression,
但也有可能是被误导了
I may possibly have been deceived.
你姐姐当时穿好衣服了?
Was your sister dressed?
没有 她穿着睡衣
No, she was in her night dress.
地板上有支蜡烛
Uh, on the floor there was a candle
还有截火柴头
and the charred stump of a match.
也就是说 她被什么东西吵醒了
Which means, something must have woken her up,
点起蜡烛想看看发生了什么
and she struck a light to see what the matter was.
验尸官的结论是什么?
What conclusions did the coroner come to?
他很仔细地做了调查
He investigated the case with great care,
但他没发现任何合理的死因
but he was unable to find any satisfactory cause of death.
根据你的描述
And your evidence would have shown
门是从里面锁上的
that the door was fastened on the inner side,
窗也关的很严实 每晚都是
the windows blocked by shutters, secured every night.
因此 可以确定的是
It is certain, therefore,
你姐姐是独自一人
that your sister was alone
走向死亡的?
when she met her end?
是的
Yes.
另外 她身上
Besides, there were no marks
也没有打斗的痕迹
of violence upon her.
会是投毒吗?
What about poison?
医生查了 没查出中毒迹象
The doctors examined her for it, without success.
那你认为 这位不幸的女士是怎么死的?
What do you think this unfortunate lady died of, then?
我相信她死于
It's my belief that she died
纯粹的恐惧和精神焦虑
of pure fear and nervous shock,
尽管我不知道是什么让她如此受惊
though what it was which frightened her I cannot imagine.
你觉得她说的带子是什么意思 斑点带子?
What do you gather from the allusion to a band, a speckled band?
胡话
Delirium.
或是戴着带子的人
Or some band of people.
庄园里的吉普赛人会把
The gypsies at the plantation have spotted
斑点手帕系在脖子上
handkerchiefs they wear around their necks.
里面有很多隐情
These are very deep waters.
你姐姐死后发生了什么?
What happened after your sister's death?
我的生活更寂寞了
My life was lonelier than ever
直到一个月前
until a month ago,
我的一个好朋友
when a dear friend of mine,
相识多年的
whom I have known for many years,
他盛情向我求婚
did me the honor to ask for my hand in marriage.
他叫珀西阿米蒂其
His name is Mr. Percy Armitage.
你们几周内就要结婚了
And you are to be married within a few weeks.
那你为什么来找我呢
So what prompted you to come here
你的生活似乎走上了正轨
when your life seems set so fair?
昨天 房子的修葺开始了
Yesterday, some repairs were started
我的房间被穿了个洞
and my bedroom wall was pierced,
所以昨晚我只能
so that last night I was forced
搬到朱莉亚死去的屋子里
to move into the chamber in which Julia died,
就睡在那张
to sleep in the very bed
她临死睡的床上
in which she slept.
想想我有多恐惧 半夜里被
Imagine my terror when I was woken by the same
预示她死亡的低低哨音惊醒
low whistle which had been the herald of her own death.
你点了灯?
You lit a lamp?
是的 但什么也没发现
Yes, but nothing was to be seen.
我害怕得睡不着
I was too shaken to sleep.
便穿好衣服溜出了房间
I dressed and slipped out of the house.
在皇冠旅馆找到辆马车
I got a dog-cart at the Crown Inn,
赶到伦敦 只有一个目的
and came to London with one objective,
征求你的意见
asking your advice.
你很明智
You did wisely.
可你全都告诉我了吗?
But have you told me all?
是的
Yes.
没有 斯通小姐
You have not, Miss Stoner.
你在袒护你的继父
You are shielding your stepfather.
他很严苛 可他仍然
He is a hard man, but he's still
是我唯一的父亲
the only father I have known.
我想到早饭时间了
I'd say it was time for some breakfast.
我还有许多细节要了解
There are a thousand details I desire to know
不然我无法行动
before I decide on a course of action.
如果我们今天去斯托克摩兰
If we were to come to Stoke Moran today,
能看看这些房间吗
could we see over these rooms
在你继父不知道的情况下?
without the knowledge of your stepfather?
刚好 他说过
As it happens, he spoke of coming
今天要来城里办事
to town today on some business.
那工人呢?
And the workmen?
我没看见
I have seen none.
我们有一个本村的女仆 来做打扫
We have a woman who comes to clean from the village,
但只在早上
but only in the morning.
那儿应该没什么人打搅你们
There should be nothing to disturb you.
很好
Excellent.
华生 你不会介意跑一趟吧?
Watson, you are not averse to this trip?
绝不会
By no means.
那我们午后去找你
Then we will be with you in the early afternoon.
我会等你们到来
I shall be there for your arrival.
你真不留下吃早饭吗?
You'll stay for some breakfast, surely?
谢谢 不了
Thank you, no.
我心里轻松了不少
My heart is lightened already.
哈德森太太 谢谢你
Ah, Mrs. Hudson, thank you.
当你联想夜半的哨音
When you combine the ideas of whistles at night,
一群吉普赛人
the presence of a band of gypsies
和他们过从甚密的医生
on intimate terms with the doctor,
还有一个斑点带子的遗言时
the dying allusion to a speckled band, well,
完全可以相信奥秘
there's good ground to believe that the mystery
就在这些线索里
may be cleared along those lines.
哪一个是福尔摩斯?
Which one of you is Holmes?
是我 先生
My name, sir;
但你应该先自我介绍一下
but you have the advantage of me.
我是格莱斯比・罗依罗德医生
I am Dr. Grimesby Roylott,
来自斯托克摩兰
of Stoke Moran.
是吗 医生 请坐
Indeed, Doctor, please take a seat.
我才不听你使唤
I shall do nothing of the kind.
我知道我的继女
I know that my stepdaughter
今早来过这里
has been here this morning.
她对你说了什么?
What has she been saying to you?
今年这时候比往年冷些
It is a little cold for the time of the year.
她对你说了什么?
What has she been saying to you?
但我听说庄稼收成不错
But I have heard that the crops promise well.
你在耍我 是吗?
Ah, you put me off, do you?
你这个无赖 先生
You scoundrel, sir.
我以前听说过你
I've heard of you before.
你就是福尔摩斯 爱管闲事的人
You are Holmes, the meddler,
福尔摩斯 挑事的
Holmes the busybody,
福尔摩斯 苏格兰场芝麻官
Holmes, the Scotland Yard Jack-in-office.
和你谈话真的很有趣
Your conversation really is most entertaining,
请你离开时
if you would close the door,
随手关门 貌似有阵微风吹过
on your way out, as there is a decided draft.
我不说完自然不会走
I will go when I have said my say.
你吃豹子胆了 敢管我的事
Don't you dare to interfere in my affairs.
我知道斯通小姐来过这里
I know that Miss Stoner has been here.
惹了我可没好果子吃
I am a dangerous man to fall foul of.
谢谢你 哈德森太太 只是个客户而已
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson, just another client.
多么可亲的人
What a very amiable person.
我可能没那么大块头 可是...
I may not be quite so bulky, but -
他实在太傲慢了
fancy his having the insolence
竟然把我跟官方探员混为一谈
to confound me with the official detective force.
这倒使案子更有趣味了
Ah, this incident gives zest to our investigation.
我只是希望我们的朋友
I only hope our friend won't suffer
不会为轻率地留下了行踪
from her imprudence in allowing that brute
而吃苦头
to trace her here.
我一直在想一个问题 华生
One thought keeps nagging at me, Watson,
罗依罗德在印度的职业生涯
Roylott's professional life in India,
如果那么成功
if it was so successful,
为什么他会回来过这种
why would he exchange it for a life
没落贵族的生活?
of aristocratic penury?
我朋友库默可能会知道
My friend Cooms would know.
库默当时也在加尔各答
Cooms was in Calcutta around that time.
找到你的朋友库默
Find your friend Cooms
看看我们从他那里能得到什么
and see what you can get from him.
我要去趟医师协会
I shall walk down to Doctors' Commons,
希望能得到一些资料
where I hope to get some data
可能会对案子有帮助
which may help us in this matter.
我们下午一点在滑铁卢车站大钟下见
Let us meet again at 1:00 under the clock at Waterloo Station.
如果到时你能吃完早饭的话
That is, if you've finished your breakfast by then.
对了 带着你的左轮手枪
Oh, and your revolver,
我要求你一定要揣在口袋里
I would be obliged if you would slip it into your pocket.
埃利2号手枪正好对付
An Eley #2 is an excellent argument
能把钢制拨火棍拧弯的先生
against gentlemen who can twist steel pokers into knots.
还有 你的牙刷
That, and your toothbrush,
我想就这些了
are I think all we need.
我看了他亡妻的遗嘱
I've seen the will of the deceased wife.
在她死时 她每年的收入
Her annual income at the time of her death
将近1100磅
was a little short of 1100 pounds,
但由于农产品价格下跌
but, due to the fall in agricultural prices,
现在只有不到750磅了
there's now no more than 750 pounds.
每一个女儿在结婚后
Each girl in case of marriage,
都将得到250磅
could claim 250 pounds.
所以 如果两个女儿都结婚的话
So, if both girls had married, ah, beauty,
格莱斯比・罗依罗德的就会少得可怜了
Grimesby Roylott would have had a mere pittance.
甚至其中一个结婚也会毁了他
And even one marriage would ruin him.
这是最可能的作案动机
The strongest possible motive.
哦 你找到库默了吗
Oh, did you manage to find Cooms?
找到了
Yes, I did.
他真是很难找
He proved rather hard to locate,
但最终我还是找到了
but I finally managed
就在巴兹的斯万松郡
to get him through Swanson at Bards.
在加尔各答他的确认识罗依罗德
He did know Roylott in Calcutta,
证实了那女孩所说的
confirmed what the girl had said,
还说了一件有趣的事
and added one intriguing fact.
当时发生了多起盗窃案
Now, it seems that a series of robberies
就在他的房子里
had been perpetrated in his house,
嫌疑落到了他的当地管家头上
and suspicion fell on his native butler.
罗依罗德当场揪住他
Roylott promptly seized the man,
在盛怒之下
and in a fit of anger
把那可怜的人打死了
beat the poor fellow to death,
虽然勉强逃过了死罪
narrowly escaped a capital sentence,
但他还是坐了很久的牢
but suffered a long term of imprisonment,
回国的时候
and returned to this country
已变成了一个阴郁的人
a morose and disappointed man.
华生 这真是个罪恶的世界
Ah, Watson, it's a wicked world.
尤其当一个聪明人把头脑用于犯罪
And when a clever man turns his brain to crime,
那是最糟糕的了
it's the worst of all.
先生们 你们是来渡假的吗?
On holiday, are you, gentlemen?
不 我们是建筑师
No, we're architects,
来看看当地的房子
taking a look at some of the local houses.
所以你们要去斯托克摩兰
Ah, that's why you're wanting Stoke Moran.
真没想到是为社交原因
I didn't think it was for social reasons.
那你们要和罗依罗德医生做生意?
You'll be, doing business with Dr. Roylott then?
是的 我想就是他
Yes, I believe that was the name.
如果不介意 我提醒你们
If you don't mind a word of warning,
要提防着点这个人 先生
you want to take care with him, sir.
当地的人说
There are some round these parts
他脑子有些不正常
say he's not right in the head.
是吗?
Really?
就在昨天 铁匠肖恩先生
Only yesterday, Mr. Thorn, the blacksmith,
和医生闹得很不愉快
had a most nasty experience with the Doctor
因为他让那些吉普赛小偷
because of those thieving gypsies
在他那里扎营
who are camped in the grounds.
对 我们听说吉普赛人了
Oh, yes, we've heard about the gypsies
还有豹子
and the leopard.
结果呢
The story goes,
医生把肖恩扔进了河里
the Doctor threw Mr. Thorn in the stream
他脾气失控了
in a fit of uncontrollable temper.
肖恩先生也是个大个子
And that Thorn, he's not a small man.
老天 那不是要被捕了吗?
Good Lord, is he bringing a charge of assault?
本来是的 但斯通小姐
He was going to, but Miss Stoner,
医生的年轻养女
the Doctor's young stepdaughter,
自掏腰包给了他一些封口费
paid him some of her own money to keep it quiet.
这就是我听到的
Well, that's what I heard.
我倒没听说
Well, I never.
你呢 福尔摩斯
Did you hear that, Holmes,
对那位年轻女士的事听得越多
the more I see and hear of that young lady,
我就对她越敬佩
the more my admiration increases,
确实是精神可嘉的女士
young woman of commendable spirit.
就停这儿吧 车夫
You can pull up here, driver.
你是指谁?
Who do you mean?
当然是斯通小姐
Well, Miss Stoner, of course,
令人敬佩
most admirable.
啊 斯通小姐
Ah, Miss Stoner.
一切都很顺利
Everything worked splendidly.
罗依罗德医生去了伦敦
Dr. Roylott has gone to London
要到晚上才回来
and he won't be back before the evening.
但我们以经有幸
But we have already had the pleasure
和罗依罗德医生相识了
of Dr. Roylott's acquaintance.
天啊 他跟踪我?
Goodness, he followed me?
是的 你一走他就进来了
Yes, he turned up just after you left,
但福尔摩斯把他嘲笑走了
but Holmes sent him off with a flea in his ear.
他太狡猾了 我真不知道
He's so cunning, I never know
在他身边还有没有安全可言
when I'm safe from him.
当然 他也得当心
Well then, he must guard himself,
不然他可能发现有人
or he may find someone more cunning
在这种事上比他更狡猾
than himself upon his track, shall we.
福尔摩斯 你不认为我们应该
Holmes, don't you think we ought to get
让斯通小姐今晚离开吗?
Miss Stoner away from here tonight?
好引起猜疑?
And arouse suspicion?
但如果他来粗的...
But if he's violent ...
我们守在这儿
We shall be here.
那么这就是罗依罗德医生的房间
So this is Dr. Roylott's room,
这是你姐姐原来的
this formerly your sister's,
这是你的?
and this your room?
是的 我现在睡这一间
Yes, I am now sleeping in this one.
啊 因为修缮
Ah, pending the alterations.
斯通小姐 我可以问个问题吗
Miss Stoner, may I ask something,
这有点不寻常吧
that's unusual, isn't it,
卧室都设在一楼?
bedrooms on the ground floor?
卧室都搬下来了
The bedrooms were moved downstairs
房子大部分都在腐坏
when so much of the house fell into decay.
原来如此 真是可悲
Oh, yes, of course, how sad.
这好像没什么可修的
There seems little need for repairs
在房子的这一头
to this end of the house.
根本没有 我认为
There are none, I believe it
那只是为了让我换房的借口罢了
was an excuse to move me from my room.
啊 很有可能
Ah, that is suggestive.
斯通小姐 能否请你
Miss Stoner, would you be so kind
进到你的房间里
as to go into the room
就是你现在的卧室
in which you are now sleeping
然后把百叶窗闩好
and bolt the shutters.
你在干什么 华生?
What are you doing, Watson?
我在使用你的方法 福尔摩斯
Well, I'm using your methods, Holmes,
检查地面上有没有被踩过的痕迹
seeing whether the ground has been disturbed.
那你找到什么了?
And what have you come up with?
我想是你的脚印
Your footprints, I believe,
还有我的和斯通小姐的
and mine and Miss Stoner's,
还有这个
and this.
如果闩上的话 没人能从这进去
No one could pass these if they were bolted.
好吧 让我们看看里面有什么可疑的
Well, let's see if the inside throws any light on the matter.
这个铃通什么地方?
Where does that bell communicate with?
通女管家的房间
It goes to the housekeeper's room.
似乎比别的东西新
It looks newer than the other things.
是的 刚安也就两年多
Yes, it was only put there a couple of years ago.
是你姐姐要求的吗?
Ah, your sister asked for it?
我从未听见她用过
I never heard of her using it.
我们一般自己去取想要的东西
We used to get what we wanted for ourselves.
是吗 请原谅
Indeed, you will excuse me
我要在地板上好好查一查
while I satisfy myself as to this floor.
不响
It doesn't ring.
真奇怪
That's very strange.
通往隔壁的通风口
A ventilator into another room.
你是说 它可能是用于
You mean, when it might have
和外界交换空气?
communicated with the outside air?
那也是新安的
That is also quite modern.
是的
Indeed.
斯通小姐 如果你允许
Miss Stoner, with your permission,
我们要开始检查
we will now carry our research
罗依罗德医生的房间了
to Dr. Roylott's chamber.
这里面有什么?
What's in here?
我继父的商业文件
My stepfather's business papers.
你亲眼看过里面?
Ah, you've seen inside it, then?
只有一次 几年前
Only once, some years ago.
我记得里面全是文件
I remember it was full of papers.
这里有猫吗?
Is there a cat in there?
没有 干吗这么问?
No, what a strange idea.
看看这个
Well, look at this!
不 我们不养猫
No, we don't keep a cat.
哦 豹也算是一种大型猫吧
Ah, well, a leopard is a large cat, after all.
对 但一小碟牛奶远远
Yes, but a saucer of milk wouldn't go far
填不饱一只豹子
in satisfying a leopard.
豹是被皮带拴着的吧?
The leopard is kept on a leash, is it?
这种皮带吗 华生?
This sort of leash, Watson?
你觉得它是做什么用的?
What do you make of it?
很普通的狗颈皮带
Well, it's a common enough dog leash,
但我不明白为什么要打结
but I don't know why it should be tied.
我们没有狗
We have no dog.
谢谢你 斯通小姐 我看得足够了
Thank you, Miss Stoner, I have seen enough.
我只想问他要不要喝茶
I was going to ask if he'd like some tea.
斯通小姐 这至关重要
Miss Stoner, it is very essential
你得完完全全按我的指示做
that you absolutely follow my advice in every respect.
关系到你性命
Your life may depend on it.
我保证 我全听你的
I assure you that I'm in your hands.
首先
In the first place,
我们来的路上经过了一间小屋
on the way here we passed a small cottage.
那是杂物间
The shill house.
你姐姐房间的窗户
Will the windows of your sister's room
从那儿能看到吗?
be visible from there?
能
Yes.
你确定?
You are sure?
是的
Yes.
那我们可以待在那儿
Then we shall make it our base.
要吃的吗?
Some refreshment?
我们先去吃饭吧 福尔摩斯?
We shall have dine shalt we, Holmes?
村里有旅馆吗?
Is there a village inn?
王冠旅馆
The Crown.
那就行了
Oh, good.
多谢您的好意
Thank you all the same.
现在 斯通小姐
Now, Miss Stoner,
等你继父回来以后
when your stepfather returns,
你得把你自己关在房间里
you must confine yourself in your room
假称你头痛
on pretense of a headache.
然后 夜里当你听到
Then when you hear your stepfather
你父亲就寝后
retire for the night,
你必须走到窗口
you must go to the windows,
松开窗栓 打开百叶
undo the hasp, open the shutters,
点一盏灯放在窗台上
and leave your lamp on the window sill
给我们发信号
as a signal to us.
然后带上你需要的东西
Then withdraw with anything you may want
回你以前的屋里过夜
for the night to your old room.
我相信 尽管那里在改造
I have no doubt that, in spite of the repairs,
但呆一晚还不成问题吧
you could manage there for one night.
好的 当然
Oh, yes, of course.
现在 我们得走了
And now, we must leave.
如果罗依罗德医生回来发现我们在这儿
If Dr. Roylott should return and find us here,
我们这趟就白跑了
our journey would be in vain.
我相信 福尔摩斯先生
I believe, Mr. Holmes,
你已经有了论断
that you've already made up your mind.
请行行好
For pity sake,
告诉我姐姐是怎么死的
tell me the cause of my sister's death.
勇敢点
Be brave.
如果你照我说的做
If you do as I have told you,
保证很快就能消除
rest assured we shall soon drive away
对你的威胁
the dangers that threaten you.
对 看得很清楚
Yes, it is a clear view.
你觉得要守一整夜吗 福尔摩斯?
Are you expecting this to take all night, Holmes?
有可能 什么都有可能
It's possible, anything's possible.
当一个医生开始作恶
When a doctor goes wrong,
他会是首屈一指的罪犯
he is the first of criminals.
他有胆识 有知识
He has nerve, he has knowledge,
帕默和普利查德就是他们这行的代表
Palmer and Pritchard were among the heads of their profession,
而这个人更高深莫测
this man strikes even deeper.
我确实有些犹豫是否该带你来
I really have some scruples taking you tonight.
这次显然有致命危险
There is a distinct element of danger.
只要我能帮上忙
If I can be of assistance?
你太好了
That's very kind of you.
在那间屋子里 你显然
You evidently saw more in those rooms
看到的比我多 福尔摩斯
than was visible to me, Holmes.
不 可我推断的比较多
No, I probably deduced a little more.
还记得斯通小姐说过的吗
Do you remember Miss Stoner said
她姐姐可以闻到
that her sister could smell
罗依罗德医生的雪茄?
Dr. Roylott's cigar?
是啊
Well?
通风口 是通风口造成的
The ventilator, a ventilator made,
一条悬着的绳索 一位女人躺在床上 死了
a cord hung, and a woman who lies in the bed, dies.
我看不出有什么联系
I can't see any connection.
你注意到床有什么特别了吗?
Did you notice anything peculiar about the bed?
被固定在地板上了
It was clamped to the floor.
它动不了 固定在那里
It could not be moved, had to remain in the same
对着通风口和铃绳
relative position to the ventilator and the rope,
或者所谓铃绳 因为很显然
or so we may call it, since it was clearly
它从来不是打铃用的
never made for a bell pull.
我似乎有点明白你的意思了
I begin to see dimly what you're driving at.
我们正好赶上阻止一起
We're only just in time to prevent some
阴险而可怕的犯罪
subtle and horrible crime.
晚安
Goodnight.
今天过得好吗?
Did you have a good day?
倒有些趣事
Not without interest.
你早晨去哪儿了?
Where did you get to this morning?
我也去了城里
I decided to go to town, too.
得为婚礼置办些东西
I had some shopping to do for the wedding.
你知道我也要去的
You knew I was going up,
我们可以一起走的
we might have traveled together.
我走得早些
I left early.
对 我知道
Yes, I know you did.
是为了在午饭前赶回来
So that I should be back by lunchtime,
我下午还有些事要做
I had some things to do here this afternoon.
我只是心血来潮跑去的伦敦
My trip was a whim.
你一直就是个小撒谎精
You always were a good little liar.
抱歉失陪了 我头痛得厉害
If you'll excuse me, I have a terrible headache.
福尔摩斯 爱管闲事的 福尔摩斯 挑事的
Holmes, the meddler, Holmes, the busybody,
福尔摩斯 苏格兰场芝麻官
Holmes, the Scotland Yard Jack-in-office.
信号
The signal.
天 那是什么?
My God, what's that?
那只狒狒
It's the baboon.
多好的一家人
This is a nice household.
我们不能点灯
We must sit without light.
别睡着
Do not fall asleep;
你的性命取决于此
your very life may depend upon it.
看到了吗 华生 看到了吗?
You see it, Watson, you see it?
是什么意思
What can it mean?
全都结束了
It means it is over,
也许 这是最好的结局
and perhaps, for the best.
来 华生 带上枪
Come Watson, bring your pistol.
是带子 斑点带子
It's the band, the speckled band,
那是条沼泽蝰蛇
it is a swamp adder,
产于印度的致命毒蛇
the deadliest snake in India.
他被咬后几秒内就死去了
He has died within seconds of being bitten.
施暴者 确实
Violence does, in truth,
会被自己的暴行所害
recoil upon the violent,
阴谋家最终埋葬于
and the schemer falls into the pit
自己给别人挖的坟墓
which he digs for another.
我想到是蛇是因为
The idea of a snake occurred to me
当我联想起
when I coupled it with the knowledge
医生能够得到
that the Doctor was furnished
各种印度动物
with a supply of creatures from India.
一种毒药 快速且至命
A form of poison, rapid and lethal.
而且不会被
Which couldn't possibly be discovered
任何化学检测查出
by any chemical test.
它可能会咬 也可能不会咬
It might, or might not bite
躺在床上的人
the occupant of the bed.
她可能幸运地逃脱一周
She might escape every night for a week,
但迟早
but sooner or later,
她会成为牺牲品
she must fall a victim.
可怜的朱丽亚
Oh, my poor Julia.
医生训练了蛇
The Doctor had trained the snake,
可能是用牛奶
probably with the milk,
用哨音把它召回
to return at the sound of a whistle,
那个哨音
the very whistle
就是你和你姐姐都听到过的
which you and your late sister heard.
我检查了医生屋里
My inspection of the chair
那把椅子 发现他
in Dr. Roylott's room had shown that he
有站在椅子上
had been in the habit of standing upon it
够通风口的习惯
to reach the ventilator.
昨晚我袭击了那条蛇
Last night when I attacked the snake
把它从通风口打了回去
and drove it back through the ventilator,
我激怒了蛇
I roused its snakish temper,
导致它攻击了
causing it to turn upon
看到的下一个人
the next person that it saw.
格林斯比・罗依罗德医生
Dr. Grimesby Roylott.
所以你 福尔摩斯
So you, Holmes,
间接导致了
were indirectly responsible
他的死亡
for his death.
我得说 这事并没有
I cannot say that it is likely
给我的良心造成多大负担
to weigh very heavily on my conscience.
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==- 欢迎加入